[Music]
This program is brought to you by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu. Let's go on from where we
were. We were talking about how systems
change with time.
I want to go back over that since partly
I don't remember where we were exactly,
but second of all, it's always worth
going over last week's
material. It does not mean I don't have
to make new notes. I always throw away
my notes to make absolutely sure that I
don't use the same notes
twice. Uh it's a very bad thing to
do. Okay. But I do like to go over the
material that we studied last week and
just make sure everybody uh everybody
has it solidly. All right. So the state
of a system is described by a cat
vector and we call it
sigh. Now up till now we've just thought
of a sigh as a thing which doesn't uh
depend on time. In fact we haven't even
talked about time. We did last week but
before last week we didn't even talk
about time. uh we just looked at the
inter relationship between quantum
states,
observables, measurements and that sort
of thing. Now we want to ask how the
quantum state changes with time. So we
want to put a time argument in
there. It's simply a vector which moves
around in the vector space with time.
The rule is that it moves around under
the influence of a linear operator. And
so we can write that s of t is some unit
is some linear operator which depends on
time acting on s at time
z. That's about the most general thing
that we could write down. So far I
haven't told you what u is but it's the
most general thing that I could write
down uh under the assumption that state
vectors change linearly. Now that's
something that as I've emphasized many
times I cannot I cannot give you a proof
of. It's basically a postulate but it's
a postulate that's rooted in uh an
experiment plus the fact that anybody
who ever tries to change it and do
something different always winds up in
some conceptual problems. Energy isn't
conserved or something else something
bad probability isn't uh well defined or
whatever.
So we'll take it as a postulate that the
way systems change with time is through
linear operators. Linear operators just
mean basically matrices but matrices
which are now time
dependent. Uh we can apply the same rule
or the analogous or the related rule
actually the complex conjugate rule to
how bra vectors change with time. So
here's some
other bra
vector and this is basically the complex
conjugate of some k vector and so we
have to complex conjugate on the right
hand
side of
zero but then instead of u we have to
write the conjugate u of dagger of t.
Remember what dagger means from the
point of view of matrices it means you
do two operations. you complex conjugate
all the elements and you reflect them.
You transpose them about the
diagonal. All right? So that's uh these
two rules are basically the same rule.
One of them just the complex conjugate
of the other. Now the assumption about
how systems change. You can express it
in various ways. You can just express it
as probability conservation that the
probability if the prob if the total
probability is equal to one which it's
supposed to be then it should remain
that way for all time. What is the total
probability? The total probability is
the inner product of the vector with
itself of the state vector with itself.
And so we always write that physical
real state vectors satisfy size si
equals 1. And we're not going to allow
that to change with time. So that means
that the that for all time s dagger s or
s conjugate
s taking the inner product should be
unchanged with time. It's not hard to
prove from that that the inner product
of any two vectors has to be time
independent. That's rather easy to
prove. Um I'm going
to I'll I'll tell you how you do it. How
would you do it for ordinary vectors?
How would you prove for ordinary vectors
that if the length of every vector stays
fixed, then the inner product between
any pair of vectors stays fixed? And the
way you do it is you take any pair of
vectors and you look at the difference
of
them. There's the difference of the two
vectors. Now if the assumption is that
the length of every vector stays
invariant stays unchanged when you do
some operations some linear operation in
particular that means the sides of each
one of these triangles shouldn't change
under the corresponding operation. If
the sides of the triangle don't change
that means the angle between these two
vectors as well as the length of these
two vectors doesn't change and therefore
the inner product or dotproduct between
them doesn't change. So from the
assumption that the length of every
vector doesn't change with time, the
inner product with itself, it's also
possible to prove that the um that the
inner product between any pair of them
doesn't change with time.
If that's true, we can now write down
more
general
statement
that five of
t in a product of s of
t is exactly equal to five at *
0 time s at time
z. The inner product doesn't change.
Okay. Okay, now plug in that ph of t and
s of t are related by this object called
u. And so that becomes ph of 0 u dagger
of
t u of t
u of t because that's what you do to s
time s of
zero. So now we have a simple
rule that five of
zero that ud dagger u sandwiched between
any pair of vectors
whatever is just equal to the inner
product of the same pair of vectors
without ud dagger
u. It's a simple elementary
theorem
that if the inner product of the matrix
element of an
operator is
equal to the inner product for all
vectors then you can immediately
conclude that u dagger u is just the
unit operator. The only way to make this
happen is if you dagger u for every
vector I mean the point is this is true
for every vector in the vector space.
The only way that can be true is if ud
dagger
u ud dagger u is equal to one. An
operator with that product a linear
operator with that product is called
unitary. It's the analog. It's the
analog for numbers for complex numbers
of a complex number having unit length
in the complex plane. Right? It's the
analog of a number having the form e to
the i
theta. E to the i theta* its own complex
conjugate is equal to 1. That's not what
a unitary operator is, but it's the
analog of that that the operator times
it remission conjugate is equal to the
unit operator.
Okay. Then we we I think we derived this
last time. I think we derived much of
what I'm going to say today, but let's
do it anyway.
Supposing now to get an idea of how of
what U is suppos supposeding instead of
allowing time to evolve for a large
amount of time but let's just allow it
to evolve for a very short amount of
time. Now this is something that uh one
is always doing in
physics. Studying how things change with
respect to some parameter by chopping up
the change into little infinite decimal
pieces and then studying how things
change under an infinite decimal under a
very small change and then building up
big changes by superimposing or what's
the right word juxtaposing lots of small
changes. So take the time interval, chop
it up into a lot of little pieces and
instead of asking what U is for a finite
amount of time, ask what U would be for
a very very small time interval and then
we'll try to build up what U should be
for a large time
interval. Uh if we know how a system
changes over every small time interval,
then it should be possible to build up
how it changes over long time intervals.
Right? This is exactly of course the
same logic as Newtonian mechanics where
you study the motion of a system by
breaking up the time interval into
little tiny segments and then deriving
differential equations. So it's not a
new idea. So we're going to take the
time t to be small. t equals
epsilon. That just means it's small. And
the assumption is that epsilon is small
enough that epsilon squared can be
ignored. Standard uh small
parameter approximation epsilon is small
and epsilon squar is much smaller. So we
ignore it. All right. Now if the time
was equal to zero but t equals zero then
u must just be one. Why is that time
zero amount of time shouldn't change the
system at all. The system evolves for no
time at all. It shouldn't change. And
obviously you should then then just be
the unit operator. The small correction
the small correction should be
proportional to epsilon. I'm going to
write minus and now this is completely
arbitrary. Okay, I'm only putting in
these factors here because I know that
eventually I'm going to want to uh I'm
going to want to
um put them in minus I. Now, the
important factor is
epsilon. A small change in time should
lead to a small change in
U times an object which we'll call
H. And now I'm going to put in all the
factors that really belong that would be
there in the textbook. In the textbook
there would be an H bar plunks constant.
Now uh this is entirely conventional
meaning to say that there's no content
in putting the I here or the epsilon or
the H bar. It could all be absorbed into
H and then change the name of H and call
it um W.
So there's no
content, none whatever in putting this i
and this epsilon and this and this h bar
into the expression. It's just that um
for purposes of comparison with other
things with other things that were
already pre-established by history
basically by history it's more uh it's
got less to do with physics than it has
to do with history.
uh we put in these factors the epsilon
of course really belongs there that you
cannot get rid of because it's just
telling you that the time interval is
small but other than that everything
else is pure
convention okay but let's using this
convention let's see what ud dagger u
equals 1 s says so we have to mult first
of all what is ud dagger ud dagger is 1
plus i
epsilon h dagger divided by what is h
bar h bar is plunk's constant of
Anybody know what plunk's constant is?
273 seconds. Why is it such a ridiculous
number?
Historical. But what the Yeah, I know.
But why what what what insane person uh
uh chose it to be such a what what
history could make it so small, so so
ridiculous? And
The plank was spinning curves.
Plank was what? Plank was fitting the
dynamic curves. Yeah, but why did the
number come out so ridiculously small?
Okay. Okay. Let's ask you another
question. Why is the speed of light so
big? No. Yeah. Why is is that a good
one? Why is Avagadro's number so big?
Yeah.
It's because chemists wanted a unit that
they could manipulate with their hands.
Okay? They had little beers and other
things that they put fluids into and
gases. And how big were the flu were the
containers? They were big enough to hold
in your hand. They were big enough to
tip over uh to do things with. And so it
was natural that the natural unit of
measure of substance in this particular
case gases should be the amount of gas
that's held in a container about as big
as a human being. Okay, maybe uh 50
times smaller than a human being but
that's that's all. Well, so the question
then is a question not of physics has
nothing to do with physics. It has to do
with human biology. Why does it take 10
to the 27th atoms or something more than
that uh 10 the 30th atoms or whatever to
make a human being? The answer is that
with many fewer atoms in that you
couldn't make complicated enough
circuitry and so forth to make an
intelligent thing that can ask
questions. So it's the popthropic
principle that
uh that if you weren't this big, you
simply couldn't you simply couldn't ask
the question. So you so you better be
that big. That's the reason that that's
the reason that plunk's constant is
small. Uh it's the reason uh that the
electron mass is so small. And so it
really doesn't mean anything fundamental
from the point of view of physics. It's
just a choice of units. And it's a
choice of units which goes back
historically to a time when people
didn't know about microscopic physics.
And so they worked with large large
numbers of electrons, large large
numbers of atoms because they themselves
are
large. Okay? So uh h bar is just there
because we're
big. H is there because you got to put
something there. The dagger is there
because you have to take the hermission
conjugate. The epsilon is there because
we're talking about a small deviation
from t equals
z. And the i is there
because it will save me writing i's
later
on. Okay, you'll see in a moment why the
i is there. All right. So, what does ud
dagger u equal? We have to set u dagger
u equal to 1. So that's 1 + i epsilon h
dagger over h
bar time 1 - i epsilon h / h
bar. That's u dagger u. And then we
ignore everything of order epsilon
squared. And so the only thing that
appears is 1 + i epsilon h bar h dagger
over h bar. That's that. That's this
term. And the other term is minus almost
the same thing.
H. The only difference between them is
one has an H dagger and the other has an
H. But our rule is that that has to be
equal to
one. All right? So that being equal to
one says I can cancel out the one on the
left hand side and set the result equal
to zero. Another way to write the same
thing simpler is just that H
dagger equals H.
That's the
condition that U be unitary that H be
hermission. Hermission means equal to
its complex conjugate. Now we've
already argued and you've accepted it.
So there's nothing new that observables
the things that you measure in the
laboratory correspond to hermission
operators. Our mission operators are
observables. Our observables are
hermission operators. So whatever this
object is,
H, it's an observable in according to
the formal definition in quantum
mechanics of observables. It's a
hermission operator. It must correspond
to something that you can measure.
Moreover, it's got to be something very
general. We h uh precisely what its form
is may not be general. precisely what
operator but every system has one of
these otherwise it couldn't change with
time so the existence of some kind of
thing called H is very very general all
systems have them h is of course the
Hamiltonian the Hamiltonian means the
energy thought of as an
operator it's called the Hamiltonian
thought of as a quantity that you
measure it's called the energy
energ sort of a redundant notation. We
call it H. We could also call it E for
energy. It's the same thing. We usually
reserve the the label E for the igen
values for the things you actually
measure and H is the
operator. Okay. Now you can ask me why
why is that the energy?
Well, what other definition so far do
you have of energy?
Anybody got any other definition of
energy?
Yeah. Okay. What's the definition in
classical physics?
Here.
Oh, we're not at the moment. No, that's
not the definition of energy. That's
most certainly not that's that is the
energy of a non-relativistic free
particle, but it's certainly not the
general definition of energy. To do
work. What does work? Changing in the
energy.
Yeah, we we could we could work at it
from that end, but to work at it from
that end, we would have to work uh
that's that's a very special situation
where you have nonrelativistic
objects, we have non-relativistic
forces.
um the structure of energy would that
would that help you understand for
example the uh the energy stored in the
electromagnetic field saying that it's
mass times velocity or mass time
velocity squared or whatever. No,
there's there's some much more general
concept, right? There's a much more
general concept and one way of
characterizing it is that it's
conserved. That's the single most
important thing about it, right? That it
doesn't change with time.
and that for certain familiar systems it
takes a certain form. For certain
familiar systems it takes a certain
form. Add that to the statement that the
whole shebang all kinds of energies
don't change with time the sum of them
and that's what energy is. So the most
important thing that uh if we if we're
just taking an abstract system and we
don't know how to relate it to any
particular non-relativistic classical
system, the first thing we would look
for in a definition of energy would be
that it's conserved, that it doesn't
change with time. We'll come back to it.
We'll come back to it today. Uh why is
this object an object that doesn't
change with time? In what sense doesn't
it change with time? We'll come back to
it. Okay. Okay, so now we have an object
which will give it its name. It's called
the Hamiltonian. And we now know that
the evolution of the system for a small
amount of time is characterized by this
expression here. Okay, let's see if we
can make a differential equation for the
change of a system with time. Why a
differential equation? Well, if we know
how a system changes over very small
time intervals, it's natural to think of
a differential equation evolving it from
one instant to the next. So instead of
looking at S, let's look at the time
derivative of S. D by DT of S.
Well, that's equal essentially by
definition s of
epsilon minus s of
0. Incidentally, any time could be taken
to be the zero of time. There's nothing
special about zero. It's just a small
shift of
time. t equals epsilon. The starting
point was arbitrary. The important thing
is that we change the time by a little
bit.
So we changed the time by a little bit
and now we have to divide by epsilon and
that's the derivative the time
derivative of the state
vector. Okay, we have we have what s of
epsilon is. Where is s of epsilon?
Um yeah s of epsilon is gotten by
applying one minus i h over h
bar. S of zero is just gotten by
applying one. So what is this here? This
is one minus and
now one - i eppsilon h over h
bar. Did I get that right? No, I
didn't. S of
epsilon is
this minus s of 0
That just cancels out the second term
just cancels out the one. So the
difference in the numerator is nothing
but I minus i epsilon h over h bar time
s of 0. That's the difference between s
of epsilon and s of 0. Now divide it by
epsilon. That just cancels out the
epsilon. And that's it. That's another
way to think about h. It's basically
apart from this factor of i over h bar.
It's the operator which tells you how s
changes differentially with time. How it
changes the time derivative of it. d by
dt s is equal to
this. Now that's great. That tells you
how s changes with time from instant to
instant. It tells you the small change
over any small lapse of time or
basically it's a differential equation
for the state vector
side. This equation has a
name. It's called the Schroinger
equation. You're probably not used to
seeing it in that form.
Anybody have a favorite form for the
Schroinger equation that we want to
compare this with? I like to spell it
with the R first.
What's that? I'd like to spell it RO
instead of R.
HR with an oom. Yeah, too
close.
And that's it. That's all of quantum
mechanics in a nutshell. If somebody
tells you what sah is at time zero, you
evolve it using the Schroinger equation.
You find it at a later time. You know
the state at a later time. You make some
measurements and sigh gives you the
probabilities for all the measurements.
That's it. That's the whole story.
There's nothing else but that in quantum
mechanics. This tells you how things
change. We already we already figured
out if you know the state vector how to
calculate expectation values and
probabilities and so forth. And that's
it. Okay. But uh we don't want to we
don't want to just stop
there. Let's try to solve this for some
simple situations. Let's see. First of
all, um you know there is another
definition of energy that I'm sure
you've seen
before. It uh doesn't come from
classical physics. It comes from
Einstein and the photon. Anybody know
what I'm thinking of?
Yeah. What's the formula?
E= H new, right? E= H
new or H bar omega. Omega. New is
frequency in cycles per second. Omega is
frequency in radians per second.
uh h H bar is the thing that goes with
omega. The other plunks constant h is
the thing which goes with frequency.
Frequence frequency times the old plunks
constant is equal to angular frequency
times the new plunks constant. Okay, you
all know that. So um let's see if we can
understand why this h here might have
something to do with this energy
here. See if we can figure that out.
Let's solve the shroinger equation. But
what I want to do is since H is a
hermission operator, it certainly has
igen vectors. In fact, every hermission
operator has a complete set of igen
vectors. So there's some basis some
basis of states, some orthonormal basis
of states which are the igen vectors of
H. Let's imagine working in that basis.
Okay. And let's pick one of the igen
vectors with igen value E. E is the igen
value. So H on S is equal to E *
S. Now what happens if you start with an
igen vector of H? Well, I assert that it
will stay an igen vector of H with time
because if you wait a little bit of
time, you'll be adding in basically d by
dt means just what are you adding in?
What are you adding into uh to s? You're
adding in I epsilon H * S. But since H *
S is proportional to SI itself, what
you're adding in in a little time
interval is just something proportional
to the original vector that you started
with. If SI is an igen vector of the
Hamiltonian. So if s is an igen vector
of the Hamiltonian, it will stay an igen
vector of the Hamiltonian for all time
because the little things that you add
in are pointing in the same direction.
This so and if you add an igen vector if
you add uh you know you're just
multiplying the igen vector by a number.
So let's look for a solution of the
equation of the form. It's it's always
the same. S now is by definition this is
let me put a little e here to indicate
that it is the igen vector with energy
e. Let's look for a solution of the form
s of s sub
e of
t is equal to or s of t is equal to s
sub e of zero. Fact that's redundant. We
don't even need that. just some igen
vector of the energy times a function of
time. Let's see if we can solve the
equation that way. Okay, what is d by dt
of s? If s is just f of t times a
constant
vector. Well, if this is a constant
vector, you just differentiate the f of
t. So the left hand side is let's call
it f dot. f dot means d by dt of f.
standard notation a dot over something
means you're differentiating with
respect to time right so f dot time
s that's d by
dt and that's
equal to minus
i h over h bar time s of
zero s
e but h on s E is just E * S
E. Did I leave something
out? What did I leave
out? Minus I E over H
bar. Oh, I'm sorry. F of T. Yes, good. F
F F F F F F F F F F F F F F F F F F F F
of T. Very
good. Okay, this suggests or suggests it
says that we can find the solution if we
just find the solution of the equation f
dot is equal to minus i e over h bar *
f f of
t the time derivative of f is just
proportional to f
itself right
now this is not such a difficult
differential equation it says the
derivative is proportional to the thing
itself we know how to solve an equation
like that. Solution to equation like
that is exponentials. If you have an
equation that says df by
dt is equal to some constant and all of
this is a constant over here a constant
time f then the solution to that
equation is f is equal to e to the ct.
If you differentiate an exponential, it
just pulls down the coefficient of the
time in the
exponential. So the solution of any
equation of the form that the derivative
is proportional to the thing itself is
an exponential. And now we can read off
what the solution is. Here's the
constant f is equal to e to the minus i
e over h bar time.
It could be a constant times that. But
uh apart from a constant, the solution
of f is
this. Okay, we've now solved the
Schroinger equation. The Schroinger
equation, the solution, the time
dependence of the of the Schroinger
equation for an igen vector of the
Hamiltonian is just to multiply by E to
the minus I E over H bar T* S of 0.
Well, what is this here? E to the minus
I E over H bar. That's a combination of
sine of
cosine cosine of I E over H bar T plus I
sin I E over H bar
T. So what is
this frequency
omega? So what do we see? We see that
f is e to the minus i omega t where
omega is equal to e over h
bar. Now suppose I hadn't told you that
e was the energy. Supposing I hadn't
told you before that that h is the
hamiltonian and that e is the energy. At
this point we might look at this and say
I've seen that equation before. E= H
omega H bar omega this left hand side
must be the energy from a quantum point
of view and from the point of view of um
of Einstein and photons and plunk and
all that stuff we would recognize the
left hand side as the energy not so
clear that this has anything to do with
uh with the energy um from Newtonian
mechanics and so forth but in order to
study that relationship we would have to
be talking about systems which had a
natural
um non-relativistic uh mechanical
interpretation and we're not at this
point. So this is as close as we can get
to a derivation of for an explanation of
why we call E the energy. It is the
thing that Einstein would have
recognized
uh as uh
the energy in this equation.
We have the coine and sign. Yeah. That
be a minus sign. Yeah. And you want you
don't want
you don't want the eyes inside. No, I
don't. Thank you.
Right. Cosine E over H bar T minus I sin
E h bar. Right. But omega is equal to E
over H bar.
Um when you when you wrote down the
equation for H You sprinkled in some
values like the H bar. You also
sprinkled in the I there and set it off.
That's because that's because
well I sprinkled in the I so that the
solution would be a hermission operator.
Now had I not sprinkled in the I would
have found H dagger equals minus H and I
would have said okay that's an anti-
hermission operator. That's that's
called an anti-ermission operator. But I
know what to do with that. that if I
take an anti- hermission operator and I
multiply it by I it becomes a hermission
operator. So there was no content in it.
I just put it there because I wanted to
give a I wanted to define the thing
which would be her mission at the
end. Other words
um foresight or hindsight I'm not sure
which but uh uh I knew the answer so I
when you got down here then E is going
to be a real
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And the reason it has
to be real is because the unitarity we
don't want the length of the vector to
change with time. You see now we see it
coming out that the length of the vector
doesn't change with time. And that was
ensured by having e being
real. So
um I put all those factors there so that
I wouldn't have to uh deal with them in
the end. Uh but uh
that makes me think uh that equation E=
H bar omega came from studying
electromagnetic waves. Yeah. Well, it
comes from studying any kind of any kind
of oscillating system.
Is there some principle that says that
the frequency of the electromagnetic
wave is the same as the frequency of the
quantum? No. No. Um no no that that's
next term. Right. We Right. Is there a
principle? Of course there is. But uh
but
uh nothing up until this point. No.
No. The point the point being that E= H
bar omega is a more general thing than
just uh photons and electromagnetic
radiation. There's a more general
interpretation of it and photons being
one special case of
it. Okay. Let's see.
Um,
oh, supposing we have a vector which is
a sum of igen
vectors of the Hamiltonian with
different igen values. In general, the
different vectors will have different
igen values corresponding to the
different values that the energy can
have or that that it can be measured. So
supposing we
take multiplying a vector by a phase
like this is not very interesting. It
doesn't change it in an interesting way.
It just multiplies it by a phase. And we
know that phases are not important in
quantum mechanics.
But supposing we have a vector which is
some superposition of energy
states. Now the Hamiltonian is is a
hermission operator. It has a complete
family a complete basis of igen vectors.
So in principle any vector any state of
the system can be expanded linearly in
igen vectors of the Hamiltonian. So
let's do so.
Uh we start with the sum over n. N
simply labels the different values of uh
let's just write some coefficient alpha
n times
cn where cn is the nth igen vector of
the
hamiltonian. What happens to that with
time? Well, the point is
that since the evolution is with a
linear operator, we can figure out what
happens to each side and add them up.
That's what that's the nature of linear
operators. That's the nature of linear
operators that you can bring them past
the coefficients here and just figure
out what they do to individual vectors
and this added up in the end. So, what
happens to this? This evolves
into summation of n
alpha n. But now we just have to figure
out what cy n does. But we figured out
already what uh what each igen vector of
the energy does. It just gets multiplied
by e to the
i e sub n minus i minus i e subn over
ht
times
cn. Each one of the igen vectors is
evolving with a different frequency.
This is quite different than an
overall phase. Each phase of each
component here is evolving
differently. But that's the general
solution of the Schroinger equation.
Each vector of the energy just evolves
with its own frequency. The high energy
ones evolve very fast. The frequency
goes around very fast. The low energy
states evolve slowly. But if you break
the uh the system up into igen vectors
of the energy then the solution of any
quantum mechanics problem is just to
write down
uh that each vector. Yeah. Uh what you
said I mean I could even classical
mechanically for a series is saying the
same thing. Well this is a for series in
time. Yeah. So I was saying even heat
conduction the higher frequency is
evolving
higher faster and the smaller frequency
it's not normally you would do a lelas
transformation for for heat conduction
but you could also do a for yeah both
both make sense yeah so I was just
generally saying is there anything
unique about this compared to is there
anything unique about it because you are
saying it from a shortinger equation
perspective so
Well, I'm not sure I'm not sure exactly
how to take the question.
Um, there's probably lots of situations
where high frequency corresponds to uh
to high energy, but uh quantum mechanics
being usually it does trace back somehow
one way or another to the quantum
mechanics. But uh I think we have to
look at it case by case. I I I it's a
little too loose a question right
now.
Um
yeah, I wanted to do an example but
before I do the example, okay, that's
that's that's all
basic easy stuff. In fact, everything is
easy in quantum
mechanics. What about observables?
observables not the not the Hamiltonian
itself but other observables other
quantities that we can measure how do
they change with time now what do I mean
by how do they change with time for the
moment let's ask how their expectation
values change with
time the expectation value the average
value it's not the average value of a uh
of an of a observable let's call the
observable
a the Average value of
a is s a
sigh. Now it's the size which change
with time not the a's. The a's are some
very definite set of matrices that
describe very very particular
observables. It's the states which
change with time. I've given you the
rule for how the states change with
time. And that will allow us to figure
out how the expectation value of
observables change with time. So only
the states would change. So let's figure
it out. Let's just ask what's the time
derivative. Well, first of all, let's
call this a
average. A average. And now I'm
interested in the time derivative. I
want to understand the time derivative.
How the average of a changes with
time. All right, we have a product of
three things here. A state on the left,
a state on the right, and a bunch of um
coefficients corresponding to the matrix
A in the middle. How do we differentiate
it with respect to time? It's just a
product of three things. Two of them are
time dependent, the size, and the A is
not time
dependent. So, we just treat it as a
product of three things. Product of
three things. How do you differentiate a
product? Well, it's sum of terms. In
each term, you differentiate one of the
factors and you add them all up. So,
this then is equal
to s
dot a
s
plus s
a s
dot. No, I don't have to bother
differentiating a. That's a fixed matrix
corresponding to some very very definite
uh
observable and I fix it once and for
all. I say I'm studying some particular
component of the spin or whatever it
happens to be and I'm not changing it
with time. The average only changes
because the state of the system
changes. Well, what do we do next?
Anybody got a suggestion?
Use the Schroinger equation. Use the
Schroinger equation for S dot.
So what is this one? Let's let's look at
this factor here. This term
s a and now for s dot I put in minus
i h over h
bar
time. I have that right? Yeah. That's
this term here. What about this term?
Well, this term I put in s. But The time
derivative of the bra vector gets a plus
i. I have to complex conjugate. So that
gives me a plus
i h over h bar
*
a *
i. Notice two differences in the two
terms. In one case I have a minus i. In
the other case I have a plus i. That's
because I've complex conjugated. when I
study the time derivative of S, it's the
complex conjugate of the time derivative
of SI dagger. The other difference is
the order of operation of A and H is
different in the two terms. Here I have
h a here I have a
H. Those are the two differences. H A
minus A H. The factor I over H bar can
be taken out. just I over H bar I over H
bar
times
S h a minus a
h that's the time derivative of the
expectation value of
a a bar dot let's call
We have a name for the product uh when
for HA minus AH. We've seen it before.
We talked about that. Yeah, we talked
about commutators, didn't we?
We did. Yes, we did. Sure.
I did. But it doesn't matter because we
actually I did. I proved the theorem for
you that says that said that uh that two
operators will have the same
simultaneous vectors if they commute. I
do remember I do remember proving that
but it doesn't matter because it's just
it's just a definition. A h take two
operators let's call them a and b for a
moment. the combination ab minus
ba in classical in classical uh
mathematics if a and b are numbers this
difference is always zero obviously okay
but they're not numbers they're linear
operators or matrices and we know that
matrices don't generally commute that
you can't interchange the order when you
multiply
them and so this object ab minus ba is
called the commutator of a and b And
it's
written just a little square bracket
with a comma ab minus ba equals bracket
or not bracket let's not call it bracket
let's not confuse it with bras and cats
but uh commutator symbol commutative
symbol is the square bracket here right
so now we've defi we've derived a
fundamental identity that the time
derivative of any observable a let's
rewrite it now a dot is I over H
bar. Yeah. A bar dot is I over H bar
times. Now what is this? This is the
average of H A minus A H. So it's the
average of the commutator of H and A.
So the time derivative of the average of
an operator is related to the average of
the commutator with the
Hamiltonian. That is a fundamental
significance of the Hamiltonian in
physics that if we want the time
derivative of
something or the time derivative of an
average
value that it is just equal to the
average of the commutator with the
Hamiltonian. Very simple. Where did it
come
from? Oh, because it's sandwiched
between
S. Who asked
me? Anything that's sandwiched between S
like this is is an expectation
value. Anything at all if I want its
expectation value, I sandwich it between
S. So in particular the commutator is
itself an operator and I can ask uh what
is the expectation value of the
commutator
and I've just written it as bar on top.
So the time derivative of the average of
a is the average of the commutator of h
with a.
Now as the
first application of this, let's do one
simple application. I'm going two
applications of this. Uh I'll do one
before we take a break and then one
after we take the
break
question. What is the time derivative of
the average of the Hamiltonian
itself? Let's suppose now we didn't know
what the Hamiltonian was. We had no idea
what it stood
for. It's some observable. We know that
because it's permission but we don't
know what its meaning is in the broader
uh in the broader context of
things. So what is the time the the time
derivative of the average of the
Hamiltonian?
Zero zero because the commutator of
anything with itself is always zero. I
mean the mathematics of quantum
mechanics is not so bizarre that uh that
hh is not equal to hh.
that bizarre. It's not hh is equal to
hh. Okay. So if I plug in for a, h
itself, I find out that the expectation
value of the hamiltonian doesn't change
with
time. Sounds like it's a conservation
law. And it is. The cons the
conservation law is the conservation of
h. Every system has an h. Every system
has a conservation
law. What more likely thing is there
than the energy? And it is the energy.
Okay. So, Hamilton question. Would there
be a physical interpretation for the set
of all matrices that age? Yeah. Well,
it's a set of all things. Yes. Good.
It's a set of all things which are
conserved. Would that go beyond energy?
That depends on the on the details of
the system. For example, if we have a
particle moving in free space with no
forces on it, then the momentum is
conserved.
So, but if there's a force on the
system, then the momentum is not
conserved. So, it depends on the details
of of the of the system whether there
are other conserved quantities.
Um but yes I mean it's a good question.
There is the collection of all things
which commute with a Hamiltonian and
that collection is the set of conserved
quantities. The set of things which are
conserved for the particular system that
you might be thinking about. Let's take
a
break. One other point that I uh that I
forgot to mention
We're going to do an example in a
minute. We're going to I mean we're
going to take all this abstract stuff
and work it out in the very very
simplest case. Namely, a spin in a
magnetic field, the simplest system that
we know how to deal with, but we'll do
it in a minute. But let me get all of
the abstract things out uh and then
we'll then we'll do it in detail. Uh a
concrete example.
Um the Hamiltonian H is a hermission
operator. That means it has a complete
family of igen values and igen
vectors. And if you work in the
basis of states described by the igen
vectors of H, then H is a diagonal
matrix. Right? Every uh H is a diagonal
matrix in the basis of vectors of H.
That's trivial.
Nothing nothing new there. And so in the
energy igen basis let's call it in the
uh in the basis of states which are
energy igen vectors the Hamiltonian is
just
a diagonal matrix E1 E2 E3 E4 so forth
with zeros everywhere
else. Now we also saw what happened
where is it? We also saw what happened
to an individual igen vector as time
evolves. As time evolves each vector
gets
multiplied by e to the minus i e h o e
over h bar t. That immediately tells us
in the same basis the basis of the same
igen vectors it tells us what U is
u is a matrix whose entries are just
these exponentials. Each vector gets
multiplied by this rotating phase by
this
exponential and the different vectors
don't get mixed up. Each one just gets
multiplied. And so it tells us that the
matrix in the same basis in the same
basis is just e to the minus i e1 over h
bar
t e to the minus i e2 over h bar t and
so forth. Everything else being
zero. The fact that the other elements
are zero means that the igen vectors
don't get mixed up with each other. that
they don't rotate into each other. Each
one simply gets a phase and so it's a
diagonal matrix that looks like
this. The way this is usually written is
just to say well this is the these these
are matrix representations of linear
operators in terms of abstract
operators.
What one writes is that u is equal to e
to the i minus i h over h bar
t. You can interpret that just in terms
of the igen
values that the elements of u are simply
the exponentials with a t here
appropriate t here of the uh of the
elements of
h. That's a notation if you like. Yeah.
If I have two different systems and I
bring them together, so I'm going to
treat them as a single system. Yeah. But
the the they each have energy components
that happen to be at the same frequency.
How do I interpret that the fact that
each vector really is representative of
a different frequency? It may be it it
can be that there are vectors with the
same frequency.
Okay. And so I just changed the
coefficient. I just that
vectors when I bring the two together
that value that well I bring the two
together I don't quite see that uh I'm
not sure what question you're asking so
I have a Hamiltonian for each of two
systems and I bring them together and
create a single system with a bigger
Hamiltonian
if if the energies in each of the two
systems have the same frequency when I
bring the two Hamiltonians together does
that mean there's going to be some
overlap in the
system with Hamiltonian A with
Hamiltonian B. They both happen to have
a frequency element that's common.
Yeah. But remember the frequencies of
the combined system are the sums of the
frequencies of the two systems. Yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Well, no. It's not because
it's linear. Um it's this is a separate
postulate if you like that
non-interacting separated systems which
are not interacting with each other have
Hamiltonians which are the sum of the
two Hamiltonians. Now we could we could
justify that uh but uh since you asked
me the question the answer is that the
energy values are the sums of the values
of the separate system. Now that's not
surprising energies add of course if
they're interacting that's not quite
true. If they're interacting, that may
not be quite true that the energies
quite add. But if they're not
interacting and you take the combined
system, the energies are simply the sums
of the two energies. The Hamiltonians
are the sums of the two Hamiltonians.
Maybe we can even do an example if we
have time. Uh but I'm not sure if we
will or not. But
uh all right, the example that I want to
do in some detail now is the problem of
a spin in a magnetic field.
Let's work out. Let's write down all the
various equations that we
need. Just a single spin. Now, no
entanglement for the moment. Probably
won't get to it, but
uh so we have the spin matrices sigma 1,
sigma 2, and sigma 3.
They represent the components of spin
and they're also proportional to the
components of the magnetic moment of the
electron if it's an
electron. And we have a magnetic field
B. That's what we
have B. Magnetic field pointing in some
direction. It's a pointer. It's a not a
we won't call it a vector because we get
ourselves confused. uh but uh it is a
thing that points in a direction of
space and it has magnitude
B. The energy of a of a spin in a
magnetic field is given by the product
of the spin and the magnetic field. In
fact, the dotproduct of the two of them.
If you have a spin pointing in some
direction and a magnetic field in some
other direction, the energy stored is
proportional to the dotproduct of the
spin and the magnetic field. Or really,
it's the dot product of the magnetic
moment and the
uh and the magnetic field. Now the
magnetic moment is proportional to the
spin. If you have a electron spinning
spin and the um what's the coefficient
that connects them?
Mu it's called mu right magnetic moment.
magnetic moment. Uh so the magnet or the
magnetic moment, right? The magnetic
moment which is a little
vector is
uh is actually the spin
vector times a number. The number is
called the magnetic moment u and I think
there's a factor of two here in the in
the
definition. Let's not let's not write
that. Let's just write here's an
interesting quantity. M Sigma / two. The
two is entirely conventional and it
could be absorbed into the mu. What is
it? What is this thing? This is the
thing that you multiply by B to get the
energy. Obviously, there's a little
coefficient here uh that has to do with
the charge on the spin. If the if the
spin had no charge, there would be no
electric current going around and so it
wouldn't interact with the magnetic
field at all. So the magnitude of the
electric charge of a particle is somehow
buried in mu here. And this two here I
think is just a convention. I vaguely
remember there is a two there. I think
there is a two. In any case the uh the
energy is sigma mu over two
dob the magnetic
field. So that must be the Hamiltonian.
Let's take that to be the Hamiltonian
where now sigma is thought of as a
quantum operator. B is just a is just a
magnetic field. It's got nothing. It's
not quantum mechanical. It's just a
great big magnet is sitting there. Uh 10
Tesla magnet. B is 10 Teslas or whatever
it is. Uh and pointing in some definite
direction that's provided by this big
heavy stable magnet. We don't have to
think about the quantum mechanics of the
magnet. And so it's just there. Okay.
Now let's choose B in a particular
direction. What's the most convenient
direction to choose? Let's choose B in
the three in the third direction along
the Z-axis. And then the Hamiltonian has
a simple form. It's just mu over two
times the magnitude of the magnetic
field. Just be without an arrow over it
means the magnitude times sigma 3.
So this is the this is the energy or the
Hamiltonian of a spin in a magnetic
field. Okay. What I want to calculate
first is I want to calculate the time
dependence of the averages of the three
components of the spin. This is the
analog of the classical mechanical
question of calculating how the spin
does whatever it does. Does it rotate?
What does it do? Okay. Um so let's let's
begin by calculating how the expectation
values change with time. The expectation
values of sigma 1, sigma 2, and sigma 3.
First of all, what about sigma 3? Oh,
let's write down the equation. The
equation for the evolution of an
expectation value is right
here. So let's start with sigma 3. Sigma
dot the uh I won't bother writing
expectation values. I mean here the
expectation value of of sigma 3 the time
derivative of
it that's equal to
I over h
bar times the commutator of the
Hamiltonian with sigma
3. But the Hamiltonian is just
proportional to sigma
3. So the Hamiltonian except for a
numerical factor is sigma 3 and the
commutator of sigma 3 with itself is
zero. So first thing it tells us is that
the time that the time derivative of the
expectation value of sigma 3 is equal to
zero. Let's draw let's uh yeah let's
draw here's the xy plane. Here's the
z-axis
zx y. And now we've discovered that the
component of the spin along the z-axis
doesn't change with
time. How much freedom does that give to
the motion of sigma? Well, it means that
the projection of sigma onto the third
axis doesn't change. And it means that
the angle of the spin relative to the uh
to the vertical axis doesn't change. So
whatever the spin does the expectation
value of the three components it must
somehow move on a cone of fixed angle
here otherwise the component along the
z-axis would
uh uh would change with
time. Okay. Now what about uh the x
component and the y component of the
spin? That's more interesting. This one
was boring. Basically this was just
conservation of energy that this is
equal to zero. that uh since the energy
is proportional to the third component
of spin, the conservation of energy must
tell us that third component of spin
doesn't change with time or the average
of it the average of the energy
shouldn't change with
time. Next, what about let's see which
one did I do
next? Let's do sigma one dot.
Sigma 1 dot is I over H bar times the
commutator of sigma 3. H is let's write
down what H
is. H is mu / 2 * B * Sigma 3. So
there's a
mu i h
bar times m u /
b times a commutator of sigma 3 with
sigma
1. Now I'm looking at sigma 1 dot. So I
write sigma 1 instead of
a. First entry here is still sigma
3. Anybody know what the commutator of
sigma 3 and sigma 1 is?
Okay, let's work it out. Let's work it
out. Sigma 3. All right. So, we're going
to write sigma 3 sigma 1. First, we'll
do it in the order sigma 3 sigma 1.
That's equal to 1 - 1 0 0
times 1 1 0
0. Sigma 1 is here. Sigma 3 is here.
What's the product? Usual
rule. First row time first column
zero. First row time second column
one. Second row time first column minus
one zero.
This looks sort of like sigma y or sigma
2, sigma 2 except uh that it is lacking
an i. Right? This would be sigma 2 if
there was a minus i and a plus i here.
So this is actually 2 i * uh sorry it's
just i * sigma
2. Let's check that. I * sigma 2 would
be I * - I I 0 0 minus I * I is 1. Yeah,
that's that's correct. So that's I *
sigma 2. Let's do them in the other
order. Now the other order we have 0 1 1
0 times 1 0 0 -
1. Okay. So now we have um let's
see first row time first column zero
again first row time second column minus
one second row time first column is
one right? Yeah. One and
zero. Now this is the same as this
except with a minus sign. So this is
minus I sigma 2. But remember when you
calculate the commutator you subtract
these two. Subtracting minus I sigma 2
from I sigma 2 itself gives
what? Twice I sigma 2.
So the commutator of sigma 3 with sigma
1 is just twice i sigma 2. Let's write
that
down. Sigma 1 dot is equal to i over h
bar mu / 2 b and then commutator of
sigma 3 with sigma 1 is a factor of 2 i
sigma
2. Now let's gather some stuff together.
The twos cancel.
I think that's why I put the two there.
I can't remember why I put the two
there, but I think that's why I put the
two
there. I * I is
minus. Now remember, these are these are
expectation values. They're really
expectation values. They're not
operators. So we could put little bar
above them and being expectation values
the components are just numbers. So this
tells me that the x component or the one
component of sigma the time derivative
of it is proportional to sigma 2. And
let me tell you what you get. Well let's
not belabor it. Let's just write down
the answer. Sigma 2 dot looks very
similar. Instead of commutator of sigma
3 with sigma 1, we'll have commutator of
sigma 3 with sigma 2. And that winds up
giving
plus mu b over h bar time sigma
[Music]
1. So we have the time derivative of
sigma 1 is minus some constant time
sigma 2. And the time derivative of
sigma 2 is plus sigma 1. Does that look
familiar?
Just a rotation.
Just a rotation. Yeah. Just a rot just a
point rotating in a plane. Another way
to say it is a very simple solution of
this is to
choose sigma 2 is equal to cosine of
uh mu b over h bar t and sigma 1 is plus
the sign I think plus the sign of mub
over h bar t. Do I have it right or do I
need a minus sign in there
somewhere? Uh the other way. Yeah, this
one should be sign.
S this one should be
cosine. All right. Derivative of s is
cosine. Derivative of cosine is minus
s. And when you take the derivative, you
have to pull out the coefficient of t
when you take the time derivative. And
that gives you the mu over h bar.
So what this
is that means that in the xy plane the
component of spin in the xy plane
rotates around like that. So the motion
of the spin vector looks like a
procession a procession about the
vertical axis. In other words about the
magnetic field. There's nothing special
about choosing the magnetic field to be
along the z-axis. We could have used any
axis. Had I done so, we would have found
that the component of the spin along the
magnetic field doesn't change with time.
That's energy conservation. And then in
the plane perpendicular to the magnetic
field, we would find it processing
around the magnetic field just like
that. Uh that of course is also the
known classical solution of the way a
magnetic moment uh would uh would rotate
around a magnetic field would process
around a magnetic field.
It's kind of gyroscope is what it is.
It's like a gyroscope.
Isn't there a phase factor in
there plus a phase factor or you put t
plus yeah that's right. I mean you can
you can put in here this is a solution
of the
equations. The phase factor simply
corresponds look down at it on the xy
plane. There's a solution where at t
equals 0 let's see at t equals 0 only
sigma 1 is non zero. Let's call this one
and
two. So we found a solution where the
spin at time t equals 0 is along the x
axis and then it rotates. Um there's
nothing special about t equals z. And
the way to indicate that is to realize
that we could have started at any time
with uh with a spin pointing along the
x- axis. And then we would put in here
some minus theta minus theta where theta
would just be the phase factor or or the
time at which the spin was along the x
axis. Is that what you're talking about?
Yeah. I'm thinking in order to do
quantum mechanics, you got to have
millions of electrons and they're going
to have separate phase vectors. So it's
kind of expectation value.
12 serious
since you got to have many electrons to
get averages, right? And so each one has
a different phase factor. No, no, no,
no,
no. The point is we're doing some we're
doing some experiment. We want to do the
same experiment with all the electrons.
All right. So what's the experiment? The
experiment starts lining up all the
electrons along along some axis and then
letting it go. So we pick an axis to
line the electron up
along and then we let it go. If we're
doing the same experiment to all the
electrons, it means that we initially
start them all the same
way. Right? Uh if we have a system,
you're perfectly right. If we have a
system that nobody's been careful to
start exactly the same way, but we just
start them, right? then we have a a
mess. We have we have a density. We have
a mixed state then. But uh but if we
start all the electrons
identically that could mean that we
start for example we start them all
pointing along the one axis at time t
equals z then they'll remain the same.
They'll remain pointing the same
way. Now of
course sigma 1, sigma 2 and sigma 3 are
quantum mechanical variables. What does
that mean? For example, supposing we
start the spins so that we know that
they're pointing along the one
axis at time t equals z. That would tell
us that if we measured sigma 1, we would
get plus one. If we measured sigma 2, we
would get a half probability for it to
be up or down. And if we measured sigma
3, we would also get a half probability.
But let's start with a system along the
sigma one axis and then let it go for a
little time. After a little bit of time,
the system is processed into the two
direction. That means after a little bit
of time, if we were to measure sigma 2,
we would find it definitely being up.
But if we measured sigma one, we would
find it with half probability in either
direction. If we wait another half
period or another quarter period I guess
it is uh we would find the spin if we
measured along the x- axis we would find
for sure that it was minus but if we
measured sigma 2 again we would find it
randomly
distributed. So
uh that's the that's the basic solution
of the problem of a spin in a magnetic
field. If you had two electrons that
were entangled,
uh, would that imply a 180° phase
between them or I I know you would if
you measured in any axis, if one is up,
then the other is the opposite given
that they're started out entangled. Does
that bear any
um what are we assuming about two
electrons? Uh, you have two uh tangled
electrons. If you measure one up, the
other one is down.
I know, but what are you assuming about
the energy of the system?
We can't say what they're going to do
unless we have an expression for the
energy. So, one possibility is that
there's no magnet around, but each one
provides the magnet for the other
one.
Okay. All right. If that were the
case, you can work out what the uh what
the energy values are and what the igen
vectors are. I'll tell you the answer.
Okay. The answer is um let's
Well, we put putting them in the
magnetic field unentangled. I guess
that's my first say it again. If you put
them in a magnetic field, uniform
magnetic field, would that unentangle
them? It might uh if you put them in a
strong magnetic field, it'll tend to
line them up. But uh not not
necessarily. No.
Um, if this is too complicated question,
no, no, no. We could, it's easy to
answer the question about two electrons
when they're not in a magnetic field,
but when they're providing a magnetic
field for each other, all right, then
the Hamiltonian is proportional to to
the dotproduct of sigma and toao. Sigma
1 to 1 plus sigma 2 to 2 plus sigma 3 to
3.
We know how the sigma ones and the sigma
twos and the sigma 3es and the tow one
and the tow 2 and the tow 3. We know how
they act on the states and we can work
out what the igen values are. There are
two igen values. Uh the dimensionality
of the space is four. That means that
there are four linearly independent
vectors in the space. 2 * 2 is four. But
the you know what the term is when uh
when there are
equal values for an operator for
Hamiltonian it's called degenerate. So
if two states have exactly the same
energy then it's then the uh then the
energy spectrum is called degenerate
meaning to say that uh uh that there's
um more than one state with exactly the
same energy. All right. This Hamiltonian
happens to have three degenerate states
and one state which is not degenerate
with it. Okay. The therefore there are
three there are two energy levels and
I'll tell you I'm just going to tell you
the answer. You can work this out. The
answer is that if both spins are we can
work in the basis where the spins are
along the z-axis.
If um both spins are up then you have
one particular value of the energy.
Let's just call it equals E meaning to
say that it has energy E. If both spins
are down you also have the same energy
E. And then there's two possibilities.
Let's call it up down plus or minus down
up. One of them is the so-called singlet
state that has a different energy. The
third that's the more the minus sign
with the minus sign let's call this E1
E1 with this sign we get energy
E2 but with this
sign down up we get energy E1 again
that's something you can check that's
why this triplet of states up down and
up down plus down up is called a triplet
and the other one is called the
singlet so we have three different
energy levels and once you know there
are three different energy levels and
you know what the igen vectors are, you
can then expand any vector that you like
to start with. Pick anything you want to
start with
uh which is some linear combination of
these and then just evolve it using the
uh well using the formula that we had on
the blackboard which uh seems to be gone
by
now. a formula that said you expand the
you expand the states and igen vectors
and each igen vector goes with a phase
that's determined by the um
right what you ask what's the question
well right you want to write down a
general state pick a state pick a state
to start
well E2 the same way oh that'll just
stay E2 but it will have that's right
it'll just stay that way any
any energy Gigg vector doesn't do
anything terribly interesting. It just
rotates with its own phase. Okay. So
what'll happen to it is it will pick up
a phase e to the i e2 over h bar t. But
what's more
interesting let's see supposing we just
picked um is the magnetic field going to
supply some energy every once in a
while.
At the moment they don't have any any
magnetic
field no magnetic field they provide a
each one sees a magnetic field for the
of the other one that's
all okay so for example we could start
let's let's do a problem let's suppose
we start the system as up
down that's not an igen vector of the
energy I don't see among these where are
they among is up down down down and up
down minus down up and up down plus down
up. So let's let's actually work out
what would happen if we started with up
down. That won't be
trivial. We start with up
down. The first thing we do is we expand
it in vectors. Let's write down what the
igen vectors are. Up,
up, down,
down, and up,
down, plus down, up, plus or minus down
up divided by the square root of
two. Obviously, these two are not going
to come into the game. It's these two
which will come into the game. And in
fact I can write that up down is equal
to up
down plus down
up bracket around
it plus up down minus down up divide
this by two and this by two.
Okay. So, up down plus down up and up
down minus down up. The down ups cancel
and I just get up down. Everybody see
that? All right. Now, this here is
square of two *
two 2 *
two. Let's give these two guys
names. Up down plus down up and up down
minus down up. Right? I have some names
that I always call them.
more and Teresa
singlet and
triplet. This one is Teresa the
triplet. So this is triplet divided by
the square of two. up down plus
down up divided by of two is
triplet
plus seymour / the of
two. So that's the starting point.
That's the starting
point. Now let's evolve it for some
time. There are two different energy
values. One of them goes with a singlet.
Let's call it let's call this er
triplet. E
triplet and E
singlet E
triplet. So what happens to this state
as time goes on? The triplet state picks
up a factor. Now I'm going to write down
the state after a time t. This will
become E to the
I E
triplet E to the minus I E triplet over
H bar T. Oh boy, we got too many T's,
don't we?
I better call it cap I better call
Teresa capital
T triplet. We'll use capital
T. And what happens to this one? This
one picks up the phase E to the minus
I E
singlet over H bar T.
Which of the S is bigger? Say it again.
Which of the tes is bigger?
Uh, uh, that depends on whether I put a
plus sign or a minus sign in front of
the whole thing. So, let's see. If I
have a plus sign, I think I probably
want for for mag magnets, you'd want a
minus sign. Um, the energy is typically
bigger for the triplet state. That's
when they're aligned. And when two
magnets are
aligned, you have more energy than when
they're anti-aligned, right? because
they like to be anti-aligned. The north
pole likes to sit next to the south
pole. So they want to anti-align. That
means it lowers the energy when they're
anti-aligned. And that means that the
singlet energy is less than the triplet
energy. For example, we could define the
energy by saying uh the singlet you can
always subtract a constant from the
energy. That won't make any difference.
We could set the the singlet energy
equal to zero. Then the triplet energy
would be
positive. Okay. Nothing actually depends
on that constant but let's just leave it
there. Well, okay. Now we have now we
have the evolution of the system in
terms of the triplet and singlet state.
But if we liked, we could go back to
this representation. After all, I mean
uh the up the up and down spins might be
the thing that we're interested in
whether they're along the third axis or
not. Uh these are both entangled states.
I might want to write it in terms of
unentangled states. So then I would
simply put back for the triplet state.
Let's see what we would get. We would
get e to the minus i e
t over h bar. Now over all over
square of
2. And now we would have triplet. So
that would be up
down plus down
up over the square root of
two. Yeah. Over the square root of two.
So that would be a two down here.
That would be one one component and then
the other
component would be something very
similar e to the minus i e singlet t / h
bar over the square of two. That'll
give me a two downstairs and I'll have
up
down minus down up.
What do I want to do? What I now want to
do is I want to pick off the up down and
the down off separately from the two
expressions and combine them together. I
want to express this in terms of the
particular states up down and down up.
So let's see what I get. What multiplies
up down?
E to the minus I E T over H
bar
plus E to the minus
I E that's E T E singlet T over H
bar times up
down over
two. But now what about the other
component? The component with down up.
It's not quite the same factor. In fact,
it has a minus
sign,
right? Minus sign from
here. So what we get for the down up is
different than the the up down. Down
up gets multiplied by
1/2. You know what is this here? 12 this
uh times
that. No, not quite. The ET and the ES
are different from each other.
Yeah, hyperbolic.
Okay, I'll show you in a minute. No,
it's not it's not hyperbolic. Um, it is
uh e to the it's obviously got to do
with signs and cosiness. What it is is
it's I believe e to
the let's just leave it this way. Let's
just leave it there. You can write it in
terms of signs and cosiness, but I'm not
going to. E to the minus I E T over H
bar minus E to the minus I E S over H
bar
T. So you see that the up and downs the
up downs and the down ups get different
coefficients. Okay. At time t equals
zero the coefficient of up down and down
up are the same at time t equals z. Is
that right?
No, that's wrong. Oh, no, no, no. Sorry.
At time t equals 0, we started with pure
up down. If you remember, so at time t
equals z,
uh these this one's zero at time t
equals z only up down. But then we wait
a little bit. This becomes non zero.
This gets a little smaller than the fact
this one was maximum at time t equals z.
It gets a little smaller. This one grows
and grows in magnitude and after a
little bit of time you have a bit of
down up mixed in the state vector. So
that means after a little bit of time
even though you started with pure up
down after a little bit of time you will
have some probability of down up. Now
you wait for large enough time and after
a while this one will cancel this one.
There's a time at which this one cancels
this one exactly and at that time this
one is maximum. So it goes back and
forth between up
down and down up back and forth between
up down and down up. Sort of
interpolating in between the two of
them. That's what would
happen. But you see the rule. The rule
is first start with the basis that
you're interested in which happens to be
in this case the up down unentangled
basis. Write the state that you want to
start with. Reexpress it in terms of
igen vectors of the
Hamiltonian and then take each igen
vector of the Hamiltonian, multiply it
by the right
phase and then disentangle it back into
the uh the original basis and that will
tell you how the probabilities in the
original basis change with time. Let's
just see if we can simplify this a
little bit. Um let's see. I think this
is e
uh to the minus
i e t + e s.
No, you know what the point? Um
what's that? No, no, no, no. You're
wrong. No, no, no, no. You're wrong.
You're wrong. You're wrong. Let me just
see.
Um what?
Yeah, that's what I want to I want to
pull out the average.
Yeah. Yeah. So, right. Uh, what do I
want to do? The average of the energy is
E T plus E S over
two. I think that's what I want to pull
out. E to the I
uh E to the minus
I E T + E
S over
two. Let me just think a minute.
Um, if ES had been equal to
zero, then we'd only have this phase
here. This one wouldn't change at
all. Uh,
If you call the average then you get e.
This is what you mean by the average.
Yeah. Okay. So what we have we have e to
the minus
i e t minus e
s
t plus e to the
i e s minus e t e t plus boy. Yeah.
Yeah. Okay. This one's going to be
cosine of e t minus e
s. divided by twice h bar,
right? Time
t. And the other one looks exactly the
same, has exactly the same factor, a
phase, but then it has
sign of the same thing
t. Now, this is not important. This
overall phase is not important. An
overall phase doesn't mean anything.
Doesn't change anything. When you
calculate the probabilities, the overall
phase goes away. So, you might as well
just drop the overall phase. Forget it.
It's not important. Do I have this
right? Yes, I
do. Okay. Notice what happens. The
probabilities only depend on the
difference of energies. That's a good
thing. They only depend on the
difference of energies. The overall sum
of energies doesn't make any difference.
Only the over only the difference of
energies counts. And you can see what
happens is that there's an oscillation
back and forth between up down and down
up with a computable frequency here.
Have I left something out? No. Notice
what the frequency is. It's related to
the difference of energies. So the
difference of energies of the singlet
and triplet state tell you how things go
back and forth between the two um the
two states up down and down up. That's
an example of a quantum mechanical
problem worked out to death until it's
uh until it's finished. But the rules
are always the same. Expand the vectors
and the igen vectors of the Hamiltonian.
Let each one evolve with its own phase
and then put it back together again
whatever form you want to compute
whatever probability you want. So it's a
uh standard ritual. You reduce the
problem to a ritual. ritual is always
the
same. Okay, I think we'll finish for
[Applause]
[Music]
tonight. The preceding program is
copyrited by Stanford University. Please
visit us at stanford.edu.